========== PAGE 4 ==========
5 Specifications
5.1 Absolute Maximum Ratings
over operating free-air temperature range (unless otherwise noted)(1)
MIN
MAX
UNIT
Input voltage
VIN, EN
–0.3
19
V
VBST
–0.3
25
V
VBST (10-ns transient)
–0.3
27
V
VBST (vs SW)
–0.3
6
V
VFB
–0.3
6
V
SW
–2
19
V
SW (10 ns transient)
–3.5
21
V
Operating junction temperature, TJ
–40
150
°C
Storage temperature, Tstg
–55
150
°C
(1)
Stresses beyond those listed under Absolute Maximum Ratings may cause permanent damage to the device. These are stress 
ratings only, which do not imply functional operation of the device at these or any other conditions beyond those indicated under 
Recommended Operating Conditions. Exposure to absolute-maximum-rated conditions for extended periods may affect device 
reliability.
5.2 ESD Ratings
VALUE
UNIT
V(ESD)
Electrostatic 
discharge
Human-body model (HBM), per ANSI/ESDA/JEDEC JS-001(1)
±2000
V
Charged-device model (CDM), per JEDEC specification JESD22-C101(2)
±1500
(1)
JEDEC document JEP155 states that 500-V HBM allows safe manufacturing with a standard ESD control process.
(2)
JEDEC document JEP157 states that 250-V CDM allows safe manufacturing with a standard ESD control process.
5.3 Recommended Operating Conditions
over operating free-air temperature range (unless otherwise noted)
MIN
MAX
UNIT
VIN
Supply input voltage
4.5
17
V
VI
Input voltage
VBST
–0.1
23
V
VBST (10-ns transient)
–0.1
26
VBST(vs SW)
–0.1
5.5
EN
–0.1
17
VFB
–0.1
5.5
SW
–1.8
17
SW (10 ns transient)
–3.5
20
TJ
Operating junction temperature
–40
125
°C
5.4 Thermal Information
THERMAL METRIC(1)
TPS562201 and 
TPS562208
UNIT
DDC (SOT)
6 PINS
RθJA
Junction-to-ambient thermal resistance
90.8
°C/W
RθJC(top)
Junction-to-case (top) thermal resistance
42.3
°C/W
RθJB
Junction-to-board thermal resistance
16.3
°C/W
ψJT
Junction-to-top characterization parameter
2.6
°C/W
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
www.ti.com
4
Submit Document Feedback
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 5 ==========
THERMAL METRIC(1)
TPS562201 and 
TPS562208
UNIT
DDC (SOT)
6 PINS
ψJB
Junction-to-board characterization parameter
16.3
°C/W
(1)
For more information about traditional and new thermal metrics, see the Semiconductor and IC Package Thermal Metrics application 
note.
5.5 Electrical Characteristics
TJ = –40°C to 125°C, V = 12 V (unless otherwise noted)
PARAMETER
TEST CONDITIONS
MIN
TYP
MAX
UNIT
SUPPLY CURRENT
IVIN
Operating – non-switching 
supply current
VIN current, EN = 5 V, VFB = 
0.9 V
TPS562201
120
200
µA
TPS562208
350
500
IVINSDN
Shutdown supply current
VIN current, EN = 0 V
8
20
µA
LOGIC THRESHOLD
VENH
EN high-level input voltage
1.6
V
VENL
EN low-level input voltage
0.8
V
REN
EN pin resistance to GND
VEN = 1.5 V
600
1500
2400
kΩ
IEN
EN pulldown current
VEN = 1.5 V
1
µA
VFB VOLTAGE AND DISCHARGE RESISTANCE
VFBTH
VFB threshold voltage (1)
VO = 1.05 V, IO = 10 mA, Eco-mode operation
774
mV
VFB threshold voltage
VO = 1.05 V, continuous mode operation
749
768
787
mV
IVFB
VFB input current
VFB = 0.8 V
0
±0.1
µA
MOSFET
RDS(on)h
High-side switch resistance
TA = 25°C, VBST – SW = 5 V
140
mΩ
RDS(on)l
Low-side switch resistance
TA = 25°C
84
mΩ
CURRENT LIMIT
Iocl
Current limit
DC current, VOUT = 1.05 V, L1 = 2.2 µH
2.4
3.2
4.0
A
THERMAL SHUTDOWN
TSDN
Thermal shutdown threshold(1)
Shutdown temperature
160
°C
Hysteresis
25
ON-TIME TIMER CONTROL
tOFF(MIN)
Minimum off time
VFB = 0.5 V
220
310
ns
SOFT START
tss
Soft-start time
Internal soft-start time
1.0
ms
Frequency
Fsw
Switching frequency
VIN = 12 V, VO = 3.3 V, IO = 1 A
580
kHz
OUTPUT UNDERVOLTAGE AND OVERVOLTAGE PROTECTION
VUVP
Output UVP threshold
Hiccup detect (H > L)
65%
THICCUP_WAIT
Hiccup wait time
1.2
ms
THICCUP_RE
Hiccup time before restart
10
ms
UVLO
UVLO
UVLO threshold
Wake up VIN voltage
3.8
4.3
V
Shut down VIN voltage
3.3
3.4
Hysteresis VIN voltage
0.4
(1)
Not production tested
www.ti.com
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Submit Document Feedback
5
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 6 ==========
5.6 Typical Characteristics
VIN = 12 V (unless otherwise noted)
Junction Temperature (C)
Buck Quiescent Current (A)
-40
-20
0
20
40
60
80
100
120
140
117
117.5
118
118.5
119
119.5
120
Figure 5-1. TPS562201 Supply Current vs Junction 
Temperature
Junction Temperature (C)
FB Voltage (mV)
-40
-20
0
20
40
60
80
100
120
140
764
764.5
765
765.5
766
766.5
767
Figure 5-2. VFB Voltage vs Junction Temperature
1.02
1.05
1.08
1.11
1.14
1.17
1.20
1.23
±50 
±20 
10
40
70
100
130
EN Pin UVLO - Low (V) 
Junction Temperature (ƒC) 
C004 
Figure 5-3. EN Pin UVLO Low Voltage vs Junction 
Temperature
1.35
1.38
1.41
1.44
1.47
1.50
±50 
±20 
10
40
70
100
130
EN Pin UVLO - High (V) 
Junction Temperature (ƒC) 
C003 
Figure 5-4. EN Pin UVLO High Voltage vs Junction 
Temperature
70
90
110
130
150
170
190
210
230
250
±50 
±20 
10
40
70
100
130
High Side Rds_on (mŸ) 
Junction Temperature (ƒC) 
C005 
Figure 5-5. High-Side Rds-on vs Junction 
Temperature
50
60
70
80
90
100
110
120
130
±50 
±30 
±10 
10
30
50
70
90
110
130
Low Side Rds_on (mŸ) 
Junction Temperature (ƒC) 
C006 
Figure 5-6. Low-Side Rds-on vs Junction 
Temperature
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
www.ti.com
6
Submit Document Feedback
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 10 ==========
point that the rippled valley touches zero level, which is the boundary between continuous conduction and 
discontinuous conduction modes. The rectifying MOSFET is turned off when the zero inductor current is 
detected. As the load current further decreases, the converter runs into discontinuous conduction mode. The 
on-time is kept almost the same as in the continuous conduction mode so that discharging the output capacitor 
with smaller load current to the level of the reference voltage takes longer. This makes the switching frequency 
lower, proportional to the load current, and keeps the light load efficiency high. The transition point to the light 
load operation IOUT(LL) current can be calculated in Equation 1.
IN
OUT
OUT
OUT(LL)
SW
IN
(V
V
)
V
1
I
2 L
f
V
-
´
=
´
´
´
(1)
6.3.3 Soft Start and Prebiased Soft Start
The TPS562201 and TPS562208 have an internal 1.0-ms soft start. When the EN pin becomes high, the internal 
soft-start function begins ramping up the reference voltage to the PWM comparator. If the output capacitor 
is prebiased at start-up, the devices initiate switching and start ramping up only after the internal reference 
voltage becomes greater than the feedback voltage, VFB. This scheme makes sure that the converters ramp up 
smoothly into regulation point.
6.3.4 Current Protection
The output overcurrent limit (OCL) is implemented using a cycle-by-cycle valley detect control circuit. The switch 
current is monitored during the OFF state by measuring the low-side FET drain to source voltage. This voltage is 
proportional to the switch current. To improve accuracy, the voltage sensing is temperature compensated.
During the on-time of the high-side FET switch, the switch current increases at a linear rate determined by Vin, 
Vout, the on-time, and the output inductor value. During the on-time of the low-side FET switch, this current 
decreases linearly. The average value of the switch current is the load current, Iout. If the monitored current is 
above the OCL level, the converter keeps the low-side FET on and delays the creation of a new set pulse, 
even the voltage feedback loop requires one, until the current level becomes OCL level or lower. In subsequent 
switching cycles, the on-time is set to a fixed value and the current is monitored in the same manner.
There are some important considerations for this type of over-current protection. The load current is higher 
than the overcurrent threshold by one half of the peak-to-peak inductor ripple current. Also, when the current is 
limited, the output voltage tends to fall as the demanded load current can be higher than the current available 
from the converter. This can cause the output voltage to fall. When the VFB voltage falls below the UVP 
threshold voltage, the UVP comparator detects the fall, then the device shuts down after the UVP delay time 
(typically 256 µs) and restarts after the hiccup time (typically 10 ms).
When the overcurrent condition is removed, the output voltage returns to the regulated value.
6.3.5 Undervoltage Lockout (UVLO) Protection
UVLO protection monitors the internal regulator voltage. When the voltage is lower than UVLO threshold voltage, 
the device is shut off. This protection is non-latching.
6.3.6 Thermal Shutdown
The device monitors the temperature of the device. If the temperature exceeds the threshold value (typically 
160°C), the device is shut off. This protection is a non-latch protection.
6.4 Device Functional Modes
6.4.1 Normal Operation
When the input voltage is above the UVLO threshold and the EN voltage is above the enable threshold, 
the TPS56220x can operate in the normal switching modes. The TPS562201 and TPS562208 operate at a 
quasi-fixed frequency of about 580kHz under CCM mode when TON extension is not triggered. When input 
voltage VIN < 7V and VFB is lower than internal reference voltage, the switching frequency is allowed to smoothly 
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
www.ti.com
10
Submit Document Feedback
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 11 ==========
drop to make TON extended to keep output voltage and improve the load transient performance. The minimum 
switching frequency is limited to about 200kHz.
6.4.2 Eco-mode Operation
When the TPS562201 and TPS562208 are in the normal CCM operating mode and the switch current falls to 0 
A, the TPS562201 begins operating in pulse skipping Eco-mode. Each switching cycle is followed by a period 
of energy saving sleep time. The sleep time ends when the VFB voltage falls below the Eco-mode threshold 
voltage. As the output current decreases, the perceived time between switching pulses increases.
6.4.3 Standby Operation
When the TPS562201 and TPS562208 are operating in either normal CCM or Eco-mode, the devices can be 
placed in standby by asserting the EN pin low.
www.ti.com
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Submit Document Feedback
11
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 14 ==========
Table 7-2. Recommended Component Values (continued)
OUTPUT VOLTAGE
(V)
R1
(kΩ)
R2
(kΩ)
L1 (µH)
C8 + C9
(µF)
MIN
TYP
MAX
5
54.9
10.0
3.3
4.7
4.7
20 to 68
6.5
75
10.0
3.3
4.7
4.7
20 to 68
The inductor peak-to-peak ripple current, peak current, and RMS current are calculated using Equation 4, 
Equation 5, and Equation 6. The inductor saturation current rating must be greater than the calculated peak 
current and the RMS or heating current rating must be greater than the calculated RMS current.
Use 580 kHz for fSW. Make sure the chosen inductor is rated for the peak current of Equation 5 and the RMS 
current of Equation 6.
IN(MAX)
OUT
OUT
P P
IN(MAX)
O
SW
V
V
V
Il
V
L
f
-
-
=
´
´
(4)
P P
PEAK
O
Il
Il
I
2
-
=
+
(5)
2
2
LO(RMS)
O
P P
1
I
I
Il
12
-
=
+
(6)
For this design example, the calculated peak current is 3.5 A and the calculated RMS current is 3.01 A. The 
inductor used is a WE 744311330 with a peak current rating of 11 A and an RMS current rating of 6.5 A.
The capacitor value and ESR determines the amount of output voltage ripple. The TPS562201 and TPS562208 
are intended for use with ceramic or other low-ESR capacitors. Recommended values range from 20 µF to 68 
µF. Use Equation 7 to determine the required RMS current rating for the output capacitor.
(
)
OUT
IN
OUT
CO(RMS)
IN
O
SW
V
V
V
I
12
V
L
f
´
-
=
´
´
´
(7)
For this design, two TDK C3216X5R0J226M 22-µF output capacitors are used. The typical ESR is 2 mΩ each. 
The calculated RMS current is 0.286 A and each output capacitor is rated for 4 A.
7.2.2.4 Input Capacitor Selection
The TPS562201 and TPS562208 require an input decoupling capacitor and a bulk capacitor is needed 
depending on the application. TI recommends a ceramic capacitor over 10 µF for the decoupling capacitor. 
An additional 0.1-µF capacitor (C3) from pin 3 to ground is optional to provide additional high frequency filtering. 
The capacitor voltage rating needs to be greater than the maximum input voltage.
7.2.2.5 Bootstrap Capacitor Selection
A 0.1-µF ceramic capacitor must be connected between the VBST to SW pin for proper operation. TI 
recommends to use a ceramic capacitor.
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
www.ti.com
14
Submit Document Feedback
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 15 ==========
7.2.3 Application Curves
-3.00%
-2.00%
-1.00%
0.00%
1.00%
2.00%
3.00%
0.0
0.5
1.0
1.5
2.0
2.5
VOUT (V)
Loading (A)
TPS562201
TPS562208
Figure 7-2. Load Regulation, VIN = 5 V
-3.00%
-2.00%
-1.00%
0.00%
1.00%
2.00%
3.00%
0.0
0.5
1.0
1.5
2.0
2.5
VOUT (V) 
Loading (A) 
TPS562201
TPS562208
C010 
Figure 7-3. Load Regulation VIN = 12 V
1.056
1.058
1.060
1.062
1.064
1.066
1.068
1.070
4
6
8
10
12
14
16
18
VOUT (V) 
Input Voltage (V) 
TPS562201
TPS562208
C011 
TPS562201: Iout = 1 A
TPS562208: Iout = 10 mA
Figure 7-4. Line Regulation
0.1
0.2
0.3
0.4
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.8
0.9
1.0
0.001
0.010
0.100
1.000
Efficiency 
I-load (A) 
Vin = 5 V
Vin = 9 V
Vin = 12 V
Vin = 15 V
C015 
Figure 7-5. TPS562201 Efficiency, VOUT = 1.05 V
V
= 100 mV/div
IN
V
= 5 V/div
LX
I
= 2 A/div
O
800 ns/div
Figure 7-6. TPS562201 Input Voltage Ripple
V
= 50 mV/div
O
V
= 5 V/div
LX
I = 500 mA/div
L
20 ns/div
Figure 7-7. TPS562201 Output Voltage Ripple, IOUT 
= 10 mA
www.ti.com
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Submit Document Feedback
15
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

