========== PAGE 9 ==========
6 Detailed Description
6.1 Overview
The TPS562201 and TPS562208 are 2-A synchronous step-down converters. The proprietary D-CAP2 control 
scheme supports low-ESR output capacitors, such as specialty polymer capacitors and multi-layer ceramic 
capacitors, without complex external compensation circuits. The fast transient response of D-CAP2 control 
scheme can reduce the output capacitance required to meet a specific level of performance.
6.2 Functional Block Diagram
2
ZC
XCON
PWM
Control Logic
+
+
UVP
3
Ton
One-Shot
6
VBST
+
4
VFB
OCL
+
+
Soft Start
5
HS
LS
1
SS
Voltage
Reference
Ref
Hiccup
VUVP
OCL
threshold
Regulator
UVLO
VREG5
VREG5
TSD
VIN
SW
GND
EN
Copyright © 2017, Texas Instruments Incorporated
6.3 Feature Description
6.3.1 Adaptive On-Time Control and PWM Operation
The main control loop of the TPS562201 is adaptive on-time pulse width modulation (PWM) controller that 
supports a proprietary D-CAP2 control scheme. The D-CAP2 control scheme combines adaptive on-time control 
with an internal compensation circuit for pseudo-fixed frequency and low external component count configuration 
with both low ESR and ceramic output capacitors. It is stable even with virtually no ripple at the output.
At the beginning of each cycle, the high-side MOSFET is turned on. This MOSFET is turned off after internal one 
shot timer expires. This one shot duration is set proportional to the converter input voltage, VIN, and inversely 
proportional to the output voltage, VO, to maintain a pseudo-fixed frequency over the input voltage range, hence 
called adaptive on-time control. The one-shot timer is reset and the high-side MOSFET is turned on again 
when the feedback voltage falls below the reference voltage. An internal ramp is added to reference voltage to 
simulate output ripple, eliminating the need for ESR induced output ripple from D-CAP2 control scheme.
6.3.2 Pulse Skip Control (TPS562201)
The TPS562201 is designed with Advanced Eco-mode to maintain high light load efficiency. As the output 
current decreases from heavy load condition, the inductor current is also reduced and eventually comes to 
www.ti.com
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Submit Document Feedback
9
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 13 ==========
7.2.2 Detailed Design Procedure
7.2.2.1 Custom Design with WEBENCH® Tools
Click here to create a custom design using the TPS56220x device with the WEBENCH® Power Designer.
1.
Start by entering the input voltage (VIN), output voltage (VOUT), and output current (IOUT) requirements.
2.
Optimize the design for key parameters such as efficiency, footprint, and cost using the optimizer dial.
3.
Compare the generated design with other possible solutions from Texas Instruments.
The WEBENCH Power Designer provides a customized schematic along with a list of materials with real-time 
pricing and component availability.
In most cases, these actions are available:
•
Run electrical simulations to see important waveforms and circuit performance
•
Run thermal simulations to understand board thermal performance
•
Export customized schematic and layout into popular CAD formats
•
Print PDF reports for the design, and share the design with colleagues
Get more information about WEBENCH tools at www.ti.com/WEBENCH.
7.2.2.2 Output Voltage Resistors Selection
The output voltage is set with a resistor divider from the output node to the VFB pin. TI recommends to use 1% 
tolerance or better divider resistors. Start by using Equation 2 to calculate VOUT.
To improve efficiency at very light loads, consider using larger value resistors. Too high of resistance is more 
susceptible to noise and voltage errors from the VFB input current are more noticeable.
OUT
R1
V
0.768
1
R2
æ
ö
=
´
+
ç
÷
è
ø
(2)
7.2.2.3 Output Filter Selection
The LC filter used as the output filter has double pole at:
P
OUT
OUT
1
F
2
L
C
=
p
´
(3)
At low frequencies, the overall loop gain is set by the output set-point resistor divider network and the internal 
gain of the device. The low frequency phase is 180 degrees. At the output filter pole frequency, the gain rolls off 
at a –40 dB per decade rate and the phase drops rapidly. D-CAP2 control scheme introduces a high frequency 
zero that reduces the gain roll off to –20 dB per decade and increases the phase to 90 degrees one decade 
above the zero frequency. The inductor and capacitor for the output filter must be selected so that the double 
pole of Equation 3 is located below the high frequency zero but close enough that the phase boost provided be 
the high frequency zero provides adequate phase margin for a stable circuit. To meet this requirement use the 
values recommended in Table 7-2.
Table 7-2. Recommended Component Values
OUTPUT VOLTAGE
(V)
R1
(kΩ)
R2
(kΩ)
L1 (µH)
C8 + C9
(µF)
MIN
TYP
MAX
1
3.09
10.0
2.2
2.2
4.7
20 to 68
1.05
3.74
10.0
2.2
2.2
4.7
20 to 68
1.2
5.76
10.0
2.2
2.2
4.7
20 to 68
1.5
9.53
10.0
2.2
2.2
4.7
20 to 68
1.8
13.7
10.0
2.2
2.2
4.7
20 to 68
2.5
22.6
10.0
3.3
3.3
4.7
20 to 68
3.3
33.2
10.0
3.3
3.3
4.7
20 to 68
www.ti.com
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Submit Document Feedback
13
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

========== PAGE 18 ==========
10. The GND trace between the output capacitor and the GND pin must be as wide as possible to minimize the 
trace impedance.
7.4.2 Layout Example
EN
VFB
VBST
GND
SW
FEEDBACK
RESISTORS
TO ENABLE
CONTROL
VIN
GND
BOOST
CAPACITOR
OUTPUT
INDUCTOR
OUTPUT
CAPACITOR
VOUT
INPUT BYPAS
CAPACITOR
VIN
SW node copper
pour area on internal
or bottom layer
Additional
Vias to the
GND plane
Vias to the
internal SW
node copper
Vias to the
internal SW
node copper
Figure 7-18. TPS562201 and TPS562208 Layout
TPS562201, TPS562208
SLVSD91D – DECEMBER 2015 – REVISED SEPTEMBER 2024
www.ti.com
18
Submit Document Feedback
Copyright © 2024 Texas Instruments Incorporated
Product Folder Links: TPS562201 TPS562208

